<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be inquired of, in the first metropoliticall visitation, of the most reuerend father, Richard by Gods prouidence, Arch-bushop [sic] of Canterbury, and primat of all England in, and for the dioces of Peterborough, in the yeare of our Lord God 1607, and in the third yeare of His Graces translation.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1604-1610 : Bancroft)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10314.4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2647</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24449187</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24449187</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27675</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27675)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1851:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be inquired of, in the first metropoliticall visitation, of the most reuerend father, Richard by Gods prouidence, Arch-bushop [sic] of Canterbury, and primat of all England in, and for the dioces of Peterborough, in the yeare of our Lord God 1607, and in the third yeare of His Graces translation.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1604-1610 : Bancroft)</author>
                  <author>Bancroft, Richard, 1544-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Raph [sic] Blower,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27675:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Articles to be inquired of, in the firſt Metropoliticall Viſitation, of the moſt Reuerend Father: <hi>Richard</hi> by Gods prouidence Arch-buſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, and Primat of all ENGLAND, in, and for the Dioces of PETERBOROVGH, in the yeare of our Lord God 1607. and in the third yeare of his Graces Tranſlation.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Ralph Blower, of a fleur-de-lis with two cherubs, McKerrow 298</figDesc>
               <q>IN DOMINO CONFIDO</q>
            </figure>
            <p>At London printed by Raph Blower, ANNO DOMINI, 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:27675:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Tenor of the Oath, to be miniſtred to the Churchwardens and Sworne-men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV ſhall ſweare, that all affection, fauor, hatred, hope of reward and gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure or mallice ſet aſide: You ſhall vpon due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Articles giuen you in charge: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all and euery ſuch perſon, of, or within your Pariſh: as hath committed any offence or fault: or made any default mentioned in thiefe, or any of thiefe Articles: or which are vehemently ſuſpected and defamed of any ſuch offence: fault or default: wherein you ſhall deliuer vprightly, and according to truth: neyther of mallice: preſenting any contrary to truth: nor of corrupt affection ſparing to preſent any, and ſo conceale the truth: Hauing in this action God before your Eyes: with an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt zeale to maintaine truth, and ſo ſuppreſſe vice: So helpe you God, and the Contents of this booke.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:27675:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ARTICLES</hi> To be inquired of, by the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and Sworne-men: in the Viſitation of the Lord Arch-buſhop of Canterbury: within the Dioceſſe of PETERBOROVGH. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1607.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>NPRIMIS,</hi> Whether haue you in your ſeuerall Churches and Chappels, the booke of Conſtitutions or Cannons Eccleſiaſticall, ready to be reade by your Miniſter, according to his Maieſties plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, publiſhed by his Highnes Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vnder the great Seale of England, and whether hath your Miniſter reade the ſame or any part thereof vpon Sundaies and Holidaies, in the afternoone before diuine ſeruice according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yea or no?</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is there any within your pariſh, that hath or doth impugne, the Kings Maieſties ſupremacie, and authoritie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall: or doe any way or in any part impeach the ſame, being reſtored to the Crowne by the Lawes of this Realme eſtabliſhed in that behalfe?</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is there any in your pariſh, that denieth the Church of England, by Lawe eſtabliſhed vnder the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, to be a true and an Apoſtolicall church, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and mainteyning the Doctrine of the Apoſtles?</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Item</hi> Whether is there any in your pariſh, that doth impagne any of the Articles of Religion, agréed vpon in <hi>Anno,</hi> 1562, and
<pb facs="tcp:27675:3"/> eſtabliſhed in the Church of England.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your miniſter vſe to pray for the Kings Maieſtie King <hi>Iames,</hi> and for the Quéenes Maieſtie, the Prince and all their Royall Progeny, with addition of ſuch Stile and Titles, as are due and appertaining to his Maieſtie, and exhort the people to obedience, to his Highnes, and other Maieſtrates being in authoritie vnder him?</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is there any in your pariſh, that doe impugne, or ſpeake againſt the Rites and Ceremonies, eſtabliſhed in the Church of England, or the lawful vſe of them, you ſhall preſent their names.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Item,</hi> Are there any in your pariſh, that doe impugne the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment of the Church of England, vnder the Kings moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie by <hi>Arch-buſhops, Buſhops, Deanes, Arch-deacons,</hi> and the reſt that beare office in the ſame: Affirming that the ſame is Ante-chriſtian, or repugnant to the worde of God.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Item,</hi> Is there any in your Pariſh, that doth impugne the forme of conſecrating and ordeining of <hi>Arch-buſhops, Buſhops, Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Deacons,</hi> affirming that the ſame is repugnant to the worde of God, or that they who are ſo ordered in that forme are not lawfully made.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Item,</hi> Is there any in your pariſh, that doth holde or frequent any conuenticles, or priuate congregations, or any that doe ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make or maintaine any Conſtitutions, agréed vpon in any ſuch priuate Conuenticles or aſſemblies?</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Item</hi> Whether any perſons haue lurked and tippled in Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes or Ale-houſes, on ſundaies or other holidaies, or vſed his or their manuall craft or trade, vpon the ſaid daies or any of them, and eſpecially in the time of diuine ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Item</hi> Are there any in your pariſh, that doe or haue propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (ſince his Maieſties laſt generall pardon) the Lords day called ſunday, or other holidaies contrarie to the orders of the Church of England, preſcribed in that behalfe?</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is the preſcript forme of diuine ſeruice, vſed by your Miniſter, vpon Sundaies and Holidaies, according to the booke of common prayer? And whether doth your Miniſter duely obſerue all the Orders, Rites and Ceremonies, preſcribed in the ſaid booke of common prayer, as well in reading puplique pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb facs="tcp:27675:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Letany, as alſo in adminiſtring the Sacraments, in ſuch manner and forme as in the booke of common prayer is inioyned?</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath any perſon in your pariſh quarrelled or fricken, or vſed any violence vnto or with your Miniſter, or any other in the church or church-yard, or vſed himſelfe diſorderly in the church by filthy and prophane talke, or any other rude and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt behauiour?</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Item</hi> Whether is that due reuerence, and humble ſubmiſſion vſed within your Church or Chappell, in the time of Diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, as by the 18. conſtitution is preſcribed, whether each one in the Church or Chappell do apply and order himſelfe there in time of diuine Seruice, as by the latter part of the ſame Conſtitution is moſt commendably enioyned?</p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether the Church-wardens and Queſtmen, from time to time doe their dilligence, in not ſuffring any idle perſons or loyterers, to abide either in the Church-yard or Church-porch in Seruice or Sermon time, but cauſing them either to come into the Church to heare Diuine ſeruice, or to depart, and not to diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbe ſuch as are hearers there.</p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Item</hi> Whether the Church-wardens doe prouide againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Communion with the aduice of the Miniſter, a ſufficient quantity of fine white Bread, and of good and wholeſome Wine for the number of the Communicants that ſhall receiue, and that to be brought in a cleane and ſweet ſtanding pot of pewter or of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pure mettle.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter adminiſter the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion ſo often, and at ſuch times as that euery pariſhioner may receiue the ſame at leaſt thrice in euery yéere, wherof once at Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, as by the booke of common prayer is appointed? And whether doth your Miniſter receiue the ſame himſelfe, on euery day that he adminiſtreth it to others, and vſe the words of the Inſtitution according to the booke at euery time that the Bread or Wine is turned in ſuch manner and forme as by the Proviſo of the 21. Common is directed, or wherein is he faultie? and whether is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning giuen by him before hand for the Communion, as the 22. Cannon requireth?</p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath your Miniſter admitted any Notorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>dors, or Skiſmatickes to the Communion: contrary to the
<pb facs="tcp:27675:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 26. and 27. conſtitutions.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Item</hi> Whether the Miniſter together with the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens &amp; Queſtmen, doe take diligent héede and care: not only that all and euery of your owne pariſhioners, doe receiue thrice in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeere as aforeſaid: but alſo, that no ſtraungers of any other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh doe come often, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly to your church from their owne pariſh church: and you are now to preſent the names of all thoſe, who being 16. yeares of age or vpwards, and haue not in their owne pariſh receiued the Communion, at or ſince Eaſter laſt?</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Item,</hi> Haue any in your pariſh bin Godfathers or Godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to their owne children: or whether your Miniſter, or any Godfathers or Godmothers haue vſed, or do vſe any other forme, aunſwere or ſpeach in Baptiſme: then is in the booke of common prayer appointed? or whether any which haue not communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, be admitted to be Godfathers or Godmothers?</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter vſe to ſigne the children with the ſigne of the croſſe, when they are baptiſed: according to the booke of common prayer? and whether he hath defected, or wilfully refuſed, to baptiſe any Infant in his pariſh being in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, hauing bin duely informed of the weakenes thereof: and whether the childe hath died in his default without Baptiſme?</p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>Item,</hi> whether is your Miniſter continually reſident with you vpon his benefice, or for how long time hath he bin abſent? And where is he reſtant for the moſt part, and what other benefice hath he?</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter preach vſually, according to the conſtitutions, eyther in his owne cure with you, or elſe in ſome other church or chappell néere adioyning, where no prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher is? or how often hath he bin negligent in that behalfe?</p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your Miniſter a preacher allowed, if yea: then by whom? if not, whether doth he procure Sermons to be preached among you once in euery month at the leaſt, by ſuch as are lawfully licenſed?</p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath your miniſter an other benefice, and whether doth he ſupply his abſence by a Curat that is ſufficiently licenſed to preach in that cure of his, wheron he himſelfe is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident? or otherwiſe in caſe he doth not finde a preaching miniſter there by reaſon of the ſmallnes thereof? whether doth he preach at both of his benefices vſually himſelfe?</p>
            <p n="26">
               <pb facs="tcp:27675:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>26. <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your curat licenſed to ſerue by the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of this Dioces, or by any other, and by whom?</p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter or Curat ſerue any more cures then one? if yea, then what other cure doth he alſo ſerue?</p>
            <p n="28">28 <hi>Item,</hi> If your miniſter be not licenſed to preach as aforeſaid, whether doth he take vpon him to expound the Scriptures eyther in his owne cure or elſe where? if yea, then you are to preſent him, and ſpecifie the place where he ſo hath preached?</p>
            <p n="29">29 <hi>Item</hi> Whether hath any perſon bin admitted to preach within your church or chappell, but ſuch as you haue well knowne to be ſufficiently licenſed? whom haue you ſo admitted, you ſhal preſent their names: &amp; how often haue any ſuch bin ſo admitted to preach, and by whoſe procurement? And whether haue you cauſed euery ſtraunge preacher, licenſed, or not licenſed, to ſubſcribe his name together with the day when he preached: &amp; if he were lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed, then by whom was he licenſed? And whether haue they or any other preached in your church not being ſoberly &amp; decently apparelled?</p>
            <p n="30">30 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your Lectorer and preacher reade diuine ſeruice, and adminiſter the Sacraments in his owne perſon, twice euery yéere: obſeruing all the Ceremonies in the booke of common prayer eſtabliſhed?</p>
            <p n="31">31 <hi>Item,</hi> Is there any in your pariſh, that do refuſe to haue their children baptiſed: or themſelues to receiue the Communion at the hands of your Miniſter, becauſe he is no preacher. You ſhall preſent their names. And if your miniſter ſithence the publiſhing of the ſaid booke of Canons, hath receiued any ſuch perſons (being not of his owne cure) to the Communion, or baptiſed any of their children: you ſhall likewiſe preſent him?</p>
            <p n="32">32 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your miniſter weare the ſurplice, whilſt he is ſaying the publique prayers, and miniſtring the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? And if he be any Graduat, whether then doth he alſo weare vpon his ſurplice during the times aforeſaid, ſuch a Hood as by the orders of his Vniuerſitie is agréeable to his degrée?</p>
            <p n="33">33 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter euery Sunday and holli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day before Euening prayer, for halfe an houre or more, examine and inſtruct the youth and ignorant perſons of his pariſh, in the x. commandements, Articles of beliefe, and in the Lords prayer, as alſo in the Catechiſme, ſet forth in the booke of common prayer?
<pb facs="tcp:27675:5"/> And whether doe all fathers, mothers, maiſters and miſtreſſes, cauſe their children, ſeruants and apprenſtiſes, to come thither to beare and to be inſtructed and taught therein, and thoſe that doe not their duties herein, you ſhall preſent their names?</p>
            <p n="34">34 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath your miniſters without licenſe from the Archbuſhop, the Buſhop of this Dioceſſe or his Chancelor, ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized mariage betwixt any parties, the banes not being thrée ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſundaies or hollidaies firſt publiſhed, in time of diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, in the ſeuerall churches or chappels, of their ſeuerall abode according to the booke of common prayer, and that alſo betwixt the houres of eight and twelue in the fore-noone. And furthermore, whether hath your miniſter ſince the laſt Cannons publiſhed, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized any mariage betwixt any perſons being vnder the age of 21. yeeres, although the banes be thrice aſked, before ſuch time as the parents haue made knowne vnto him their conſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and whether hath he married any of another Dioceſſe, who are they? and by what authoritie, and when?</p>
            <p n="35">35 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your miniſter euery ſunday, bid holidaies and faſting daies, as by the booke of common prayer is appointed?</p>
            <p n="36">36 <hi>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> whether doth your miniſter euery 6 monethes, denounce in his pariſh, all ſuch of his pariſh as doe perſeuer in the ſentence of excommunication, not ſeeking to be abſolued, and whether hath he admitted into the church any perſon excommunicat, without a certificat of his abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinary or other competent iudge?</p>
            <p n="37">37 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your miniſter being a preacher, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor and labor dilligently, to reclaime the popiſh recuſants, in his pariſh from their errors: if there be any ſuch abiding? and whether is he painefull in viſiting the ſicke according to the booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer?</p>
            <p n="38">38 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your parſon vicar or curat, to frequent or to be ouer-conuerſant with, or a fauorer of recuſants, whereby he is ſuſpected not to be ſincere in religion.</p>
            <p n="39">39 <hi>Item</hi> Whether doe you know or haue heard of any payment, compoſition or agreement, to, or with the Buſhop, Chancellor, or any inferior officer Eccleſiaſtical, for ſuppreſſing or concealing of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, or other Eccleſiaſticall cenſure, of, or againſt any recuſant? what ſumme of money, or other conſideration hath bin receiued or promiſed? by, or to any of them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſpect, by whom?
<pb facs="tcp:27675:5"/> and with whom? and for what ſumme or other conſideration?</p>
            <p n="40">40 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is there in your Church or Chappell one parchment Regiſter booke, prouided for Chriſtnings, Mariages, and Burials, and whether is the ſame duely and exactly kept ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Conſtitutions in that behalfe prouided?</p>
            <p n="41">41 <hi>Item,</hi> whether hath your miniſter or any other preacher bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed children, ſolemnized Mariage, churched any woman, or mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred the holy Communion in any priuate houſe or houſes, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as by law is allowed yea or no? if yea, then where? whom? when and how often hath he offended in any of the Premiſſes?</p>
            <p n="42">42 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath your miniſter taken vpon him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point any publicque or priuate Faſts, prophecies, or exerciſes not approued and eſtabliſhed by Law or publique authoritie, or hath he attempted vpon any pretence eyther of poſſeſſion or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, by faſting and prayer to caſt out deuils yea or no?</p>
            <p n="43">43 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath your miniſter or any other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: within your pariſh vſed to meete in any priuat houſe or other place, there to conſult togither, how to impeach or depraue the booke of common prayer, or the doctrine or diſcipline of the church of England, if yea, then you ſhall preſent them all?</p>
            <p n="44">44 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your miniſter vſe ſuch decency and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines in his apparell, as by the 74 conſtitution is inioyned?</p>
            <p n="45">45 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doe you know any in your pariſh that hauing heretofore taken vpon him or them, the order of Prieſt-hood or of a Deacon hath ſince relinquiſhed the ſame, and betaken himſelfe in the courſe of his life as a lay-man neglecting his vocation, if yea, then you ſhall preſent his name, and the place of his abode?</p>
            <p n="46">46 <hi>Item,</hi> Doth any take vpon him to teach Schoole in your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh without ſpeciall licence of his ordinary? and whether doth your Schoolemaiſter bring his Schollers to the church to heare diuine ſeruice and ſermons?</p>
            <p n="47">47 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your miniſter noted or defamed to haue obteined his benefice by ſymony, or reputed to be an incontinent perſon, a common drunkard, a common gamſter, or player at dice, or faulty in any other crime puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſtical cenſures, whereby he is offenſiue and ſcandalous to his function or miniſtery.</p>
            <p n="48">48 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue you prouided the booke of common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb facs="tcp:27675:6"/> lately ſet forth by his Maieſties authoritie, and the booke of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and whether haue you in your Church or chappell a Fonts of ſtone ſet vp in the ancient vſuall place, a conuenient and decent Communion table with a carpet of ſilke, or ſome other decents ſtuffe, and a taire linnen cloth to lay thereon at the Communion time: and whether is the ſame Table then placed in ſuch conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſort within the Chauncell or church, as that the miniſter may be beſt heard in his prayer and adminiſtration, and that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number may communicate: And whether are the x. comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements ſet vpon the Eaſt ende of your Church or Chappell, where the people may beſt ſée and read them, and other ſentences of holy ſcripture written on the walls likewiſe for that purpoſe?</p>
            <p n="49">49 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue you a conuenient ſeate for your mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to reade ſeruice in, together with a comely Pulpit ſet vp in a conuenient place, with a decent cloth or cuſhion for the ſame: a comely large ſurplice, a faire Communion cup of gold, ſiluer, or other pure mettle, and a couer agreeable for the ſame, with all other things and ornaments neceſſarie for the celebration of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice and adminiſtration of the Sacraments?</p>
            <p n="50">50 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether are your church or chappels with the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels thereof, and your parſonage or vickeredge houſe and all other houſing thereto belonging in good reparations, and decent and comely kept as well within as without, the ſeates well maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a ſure coffer with thrée lockes and keyes for the ſafe kéeping of your Regiſter booke, your churchyards wel fenced &amp; kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abuſe, if not, then through whoſe default and what defects are?</p>
            <p n="51">51 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue you or your predeceſſors Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens there ſuffered ſince the laſt pardon, any plaies, feaſts, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, churchales, drinkings, or any other prophane vſages, to be kept in your church chappels or church-yard, or bels to be rung ſuperſtitiouſly vpon hollidaies or dayes abrogated by Lawe?</p>
            <p n="52">52 <hi>Item,</hi> How many inhabitants within your pariſh, men or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aboue th'age of 16 yéeres, do refuſe to frequent diuine ſeruice eſtabliſhed by publique authoritie of this realme, or to receiue the holy Communion, what be their names, and of what degrée ſtate or trade of life are they, you are to preſent then all of both ſorts?</p>
            <p n="53">53 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doe any of the inhabitants of your ſaid pariſh entertaine within their houſe any ſoiorners, lodgers, or any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:27675:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> reſorters and gueſts, who refuſe to frequent diuine ſeruice, or receiue the holy Communion as aforeſaid, what be their names? of what qualitie or condition they are?</p>
            <p n="54">54 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether are any of the ſaid popiſh recuſants of inſolent behauiour not without publique offence, or doe boldly buiſy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſeducing &amp; withdrawing others, either abroad or in their owne families by inſtructing their children in popiſh religion, or by refuſing to entertaine any eſpecially in place of greateſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice or truſt, but ſuch as concurre with them in opinion of religion?</p>
            <p n="55">55 <hi>Item,</hi> How long the ſaid popiſh Recuſants haue obſtinately abſtained, eyther from diuine ſeruice or from the Communion as is aforeſaid: Whether of any long time, or onely ſince his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties raigne?</p>
            <p n="56">56 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your Miniſter a preacher ſufficiently qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and if he be, whether doth he from time to time offer quiet and temperate conference to reclaime the ſaid popiſh Recuſants from their errors: and whether they or any of them doe refuſe ſuch conference with your Miniſter or any other Preacher, who ſhall preſent vnto them his dilligence in that behalfe?</p>
            <p n="57">57 <hi>Item,</hi> What perſons aforeſaid within your pariſh either for th'offence aforeſaid, or for any other Contumacy, or crime, doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine excommunicat, what be their names and for what cauſe, and how long they haue ſo ſtood excommunicate?</p>
            <p n="58">58 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether were you the Churchwardens and Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men choſen by the conſent of the Miniſter and pariſhioners: and whether haue the churchwardens before you, giuen vp a iuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt for their time and deliuered to you their ſucceſſors whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer money or other things of right belonging to the Church, which was in their hands, and whether doe you and euery of you diligently ſée that all the Pariſhioners doe duely reſort to their church euery ſunday and holiday, and there continue the whole time of diuine ſeruice, and none to walke or ſtand idle, or talking in church or churchportch, or churchyard during that time: and whether doe all the pariſhioners and their families accordingly frequent their pariſh church, and there behaue themſelues ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, attentiuely and decently, all the time of diuine ſeruice, yea or no? if no, then you ſhall preſent their names?</p>
            <p n="59">59 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doe all perſons aboue th'age of 16 yéeres, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:27675:7"/> reſort to heare diuine ſeruice vpon ſundayes and hollidayes approued, and whether hath each one of your pariſhioners, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboue th'age of 16. yéeres aforeſaid) receiued the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion thrice this laſt yéere, chiefely once at Eaſter in your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh church knéeling, if no, then you ſhall preſent their names which haue not ſo done?</p>
            <p n="60">60 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue you a fit pariſh Clarke aged twenty yeeres at leaſt of honeſt conuerſation, and ſufficent for reading and writing, and whether he be paide his wages without frauds according to the moſt auncient cuſtome of your pariſh, if not, then by whom is be ſo defrauded and denied? and whether he be choſen by the parſon or vicar or by whom?</p>
            <p n="61">61 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue any in your pariſh béene maried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the prohibited degrées, forbidden by the Lawe of God, and expreſſed in a certaine table publiſhed by authoritie in <hi>Anno,</hi> 1563 if yea, then you ſhall preſent their names, and whether haue you the ſaid Table publiquely ſet vp in your church, and faſtened to ſome conuenient place there?</p>
            <p n="62">62 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth any heretofore diuorced kéepe company with any other at bed and at boord? what be their names? When and where were they maried?</p>
            <p n="63">63 <hi>Item,</hi> Doth your miniſter vſe the forme of thankes-giuing to women after Childe-birth, and whether hath he admitted any therevnto, that was begotten with child in adultery or fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without licence of his ordinarie, and whether haue any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried wiues refuſed to come to church according to the booke of common prayer, to giue God thankes after child-birth, if any be faulty herein you ſhall preſent their names?</p>
            <p n="64">64 <hi>Item</hi> Whether haue you any in your pariſh which heretofore being popiſh recuſants or ſectuaries, haue ſince conformed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and come to church to heare diuine ſeruice and receiue the Sacraments if yea, then who they are, and how long ſi'thence haue they ſo conformed themſelues, and whether doe they ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine and abide in that conformitie?</p>
            <p n="65">65 <hi>Item,</hi> What recuſant papiſts are there in your pariſh, and whether doe they or any of them kéepe any Schoole-maiſter in their houſe, which commeth not to church to heare diuine ſeruice and receiue the Communion? what is his name, and how long
<pb facs="tcp:27675:7"/> hath be taught?</p>
            <p n="66">66 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue you any in your pariſh to your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or by common fame and report, any which haue committed adulterie fornication or inceſt, which haue not bin publiquely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to your knowledge? if yea, then with whom? Are there any which are or by common fame and report are reputed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to be common drunkards, blaſphemers of Gods holy name, common and vſuall ſwearers, filthy ſpeakers, Vſurers, ſymoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icall perſons, Fighters, Brawlers, or Quarellers in church, or churchyard, you ſhall not faile to preſent their names?</p>
            <p n="67">67 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue any in your pariſh receiued or harbored any woman gotten with childe out of Wedlocke, and ſuffered them to depart againe without puniſhment firſt inflicted on them by their ordinary, you ſhall truely preſent as well the partie har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring as harbored, and who is ſuſpected to be father of her child?</p>
            <p n="68">68 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath any perſon within your pariſh promiſed or payed any ſumme of money or other reward directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by himſelfe or any other, or committed his or her pennance for any inceſt, adultery, fornication, or any other Eccleſiaſticall crime, if ſo, then with whom? when? and for what? and how hath the ſame béene imployed?</p>
            <p n="69">69 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your Chancelor, and euery other inferior Eccleſiaſticall iudge a maiſter of Artes, or Batchelor of Lawes at the leaſt, and learned and practiſed in the ciuill and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Lawes, a man of good life and conuerſation and zealouſly affected in Religion?</p>
            <p n="70">70 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether any perſon or perſons ſuſpected or detected heretofore of incontinency, and therefore departing out of your pariſh for a ſeaſon is now returned againe, or in what place elſe is he or ſhe now abiding to your knowledge or as you haue heard? you ſhall not faile to preſent the whole truth in that behalfe?</p>
            <p n="71">71 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether are there in your pariſh any Wills not yet proued, or goods of the dead dying inteſtate left vn-adminiſtred by authoritie of the ordinarie in that behalfe? you ſhal not faile to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Executors, and all other faulty and culpable therein?</p>
            <p n="72">72 <hi>Item,</hi> Hath any Chancellor, Commiſſary, Arch-deacon, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, or any other exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſ-diction within this your Dioceſſe, or any Regiſter, Apparator, or Miniſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
<pb facs="tcp:27675:8"/> to the ſame Eccleſiaſticall courts, exacted extra-ordinary or greater ſées then heretofore of late haue béene accuſtomed, and whether is there a table of the rates of all fées ſet vp in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Courts and Offices or whether they or any of them haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpon them th'office of Informers or Promotors to the courts, or any other way abuſed themſelues in their Offices contrary to the Lawe and Cannons in that caſe prouided?</p>
            <p n="73">73 <hi>Item,</hi> Doe any, of, or within your Pariſh affirme, or haue any affirmed that the ſacred ſynode of this nation aſſembled by the Kings authoritie, is not the true church of England by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation: or hath or doth any of your pariſh affirme, that no perſons eyther of the Clergie or Laitie, that were not pertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent in the ſaid late Synode, are ſubiect to the decrees there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, made and ratified by the Kings ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame authoritie: becauſe they gaue not vp their voices vnto them, yée ſhall preſent their names?</p>
            <p n="74">74 <hi>Item,</hi> Is there any among you, that haue or doe depraue the foreſaid late Synode, ſaying or affirming, that the ſame was a company of ſuch perſons as did conſpire togither againſt godly and religious profeſſors of the Goſpell, and that therefore both they and their proceedings in that behalfe are and ought to be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed and contemned or words to the like effect, you ſhall not faile to preſent their names?</p>
            <p n="75">75 <hi>Item,</hi> What number of Apparators hath euery ſeueral iudge Eccleſiaſticall, and wherein, and in what manner is the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ouer-burthened and grieued by the ſaid Apparators?</p>
            <p n="76">76 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doe you know of any other matter of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall cogniſance, worthy the preſentment in your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aboue not expreſſed, which you holde fit to be reformed, and if you doe, you ſhall likewiſe preſent the ſame by vertue of your Oaths?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27675:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
